Stanford University.
What I had prepared for tonight was a
lesson
on how
string theory
gave a resolution to the question
of the entropy, what is it that carries
the entropy of a black hole.
I don't know if we'll make it all
through it because it's late already,
but let's start it.
To say that a system has an entropy
a large entropy in particular
is another way of saying that there's a
large number of microscopic degrees of
freedom which are too small and too
numerous for you to keep track of.
So, when somebody says the bathtub full
of hot water has a entropy of 10 to the
30th or whatever it happens to be
they're implicitly making a statement
that there is microscopic structure
there which you can't see.
Well, maybe you can see it, but
uh, but you choose not to see it.
You
too many particles, too numerous
and
uh, that they are carrying
10 to the 30th bits of information which
for practical purposes is hidden.
So
it
then becomes a question that you can
ask, all right, you do the
thermodynamics, you study water you heat
it a little bit, you measure its energy,
you measure its temperature, you use the
laws of thermodynamics and you discover
that it has a certain entropy and so
forth. It then becomes a question, what
is it? What are those microscopic
degrees of freedom that are carrying the
uh, entropy?
Given that it has an entropy, you know
they're there.
But that doesn't tell you what those
degrees of freedom are. It doesn't tell
you what those objects are.
Uh, and the same is true of a black
hole.
The same is true of general relativity
in particular.
But in particular a black hole
when
Bekenstein put forward the idea that
black holes have entropy the natural
question was what are these tiny
microscopic things
which apparently in some way are on the
surface of the black hole because he
said the entropy was proportional to the
area.
But there was nothing in the general
theory of relativity
which gave any clue as to what they
might be.
Uh
the reason
is not so different than the statement
that if you study fluid dynamics, fluid
dynamics makes no real reference to the
microscopic nature of fluids.
What does it do? It's a sort of
coarse-grained
description of the macroscopic flow of
fluids.
There's a velocity at every point in the
fluid, there's a density of the fluid
a few
things like that and it makes no
reference to the microscopic theory.
But when you change the temperature of
the fluid, you change the energy of the
fluid, you discover there's an entropy
and it tells you there's a microscopic
structure there.
Just like fluid dynamics doesn't tell
you what that fluid dynamics together
with some thermodynamics
does not tell you what that fundamental
microscopic structure is. It tells you
it's there.
Uh
and you know, invites you
to
start to consider the question of what
is there beyond the simple fluid
dynamics questions you could ask. In the
same way
the entropy of black holes invited us to
start asking, is there a microscopic
structure
to black holes or to gravitational
fields
or to space-time or whatever
that that is explaining this entropy.
Now, string theory did provide an
explanation of the entropy of black
holes.
It may not be the only explanation.
String theory might not be the right
theory of black holes, might not be the
right theory of nature, we don't know.
But within the context of string theory
it provided a picture and an explanation
of what the microscopic objects are
that carry the entropy of the black
hole.
So, I thought I would take you through
the very, very simplest
way
of
and it's not so simple.
But the simplest example of counting the
entropy of a black hole
using string theory.
Fortunately, you don't have to know too
much about string theory, very little in
fact.
The argument is
basically qualitative.
Unfortunately, it's a little bit too
crude to see any absolute exactness, but
it's good enough to get the to get the
order of magnitude answer right. So,
we'll we'll go through that.
Um
the first thing you need to know
is
some
facts about the constants of string
theory and gravity.
First thing is both in gravitation and
in string theory there's a unit of
length.
The unit of length that's important for
the structure of strings is different
than the unit of length that's important
to the structure of gravity.
The
gravitational length scale is called the
Planck length.
All right. Let's call it L sub P.
It's some combination, somebody remember
it that uh
it contains G, H bar and C. I can't
remember what it is.
Square root of G H bar over C cubed,
does that ring a bell?
Uh
that sounds right. That's the Planck
length, 10 to the minus 33 cm, very,
very small. We're going to work with
units in which H bar equals C equals 1.
So, in those units
G
or the square root of G
is just the Planck length.
That's all it is. Newton's constant in
units like this
the square root of it is the Planck
length. Or to write it another way, the
Planck length squared
is Newton's constant.
Now, Newton's constant has another
meaning of course. Newton's constant is
the constant of gravitation, tells you
the force law between between massive
objects. We'll come back to this in a
minute. Main point now is that Newton's
constant has units of area.
That's why we say that the that the
entropy of a black hole is its area
measured in Planck units. It's its area
measured
in units of G.
Okay, that's uh, one statement.
Now, what about string theory?
String theory also has a unit of length.
It's not the Planck length and I'll tell
you what it is.
Um
if you were to
take a typical string in string theory
heat it up
you would find out that it wiggles all
over the place.
But you would find out that if you
looked at it through a microscope
that the size of the wiggles
would be of a particular characteristic
size scale.
You would find out that uh, that the
wiggles were never on a smaller smaller
scale than a certain scale and that
scale is called the string length scale.
It's not terribly important exactly how
it's defined.
It is the roughly speaking, it's the
size of an oscillating string if it has
one unit of oscillation. So, it's a
certain length scale that goes into
string theory.
It has to do with the wiggleness of
strings in the
length scale along which it wiggles. But
whatever it is, it's called L string.
All right, so there's something called L
string.
Also something called L string squared,
but for the moment there's L string.
And finally, there's another constant in
string theory
and it's the string coupling constant.
Anybody remember what the string
coupling constant is? What it what
first first of all, what its meaning is?
Tension, length, mass, probability.
Probability.
Probability that if a string
crosses itself, it breaks.
All right.
So, it's the probability that if you
have a string
and
it pinches off like this, it's the
probability that it breaks.
And it's called G.
It's the amplitude for the string to
break.
It plays the same role in string theory
as the electric charge does in
electrodynamics. In electrodynamics, the
electric charge is the amplitude
for a charged particle to emit a photon.
The string coupling constant is the
amplitude for an oscillating string to
emit
a small string. The small string is, of
course, a graviton.
So, it's the amplitude
for a oscillating string, whatever it's
doing, to emit a graviton.
Finally,
let's talk about gravitational forces.
How do we think first electromagnetic
forces? How do we think about
electromagnetic forces?
We draw a Feynman diagram and a photon
is exchanged.
Now, this should be taken with a little
bit of a grain of salt.
It's not exactly really a photon being
shot from one charged particle to
another,
but the diagram
uh
has some real meaning.
There is an emission of a photon over
here.
The amplitude for that is e, the
electric charge.
And there's an absorption of a photon
over here.
Another factor of electric charge.
Two factors of electric charge.
The meaning of that,
in common language,
is that the force between two charged
particles caused by the photon is
proportional to the product of the two
charges.
One
for emission, one for absorption.
Well, what about gravity?
If gravity is controlled by string
theory,
then the analogous thing would be two
objects,
both of which are made out of string.
Everything is made out of string in
string theory.
One
emits a graviton. Here goes Here it is.
It's wiggling around. It emits a
graviton.
The amplitude for that is g.
The graviton goes over to this side here
and reconnects
with that.
In string theory, that is the source of
the gravitational interaction between
two objects. It's analogous to the
Feynman diagram
of
of electrodynamics.
And the main point
is that the force between two massive
objects
is proportional to the square of the
string coupling constant. One for
absorption, one for emission.
It also contains, incidentally, the
product of the masses of the object
and the distance between between them
squared, but that's not so important.
The important thing is that this g
squared appears in the force law.
Well, there's another object that
sometimes appears in the force law. It's
not little g squared. What is it?
It's big G.
The usual Newtonian force,
you put big G, not big G squared, but
little g.
So, it sounds very much
like little g squared must be big G.
But that's not quite true because they
have different dimensions.
Big G has units of length squared.
Little g,
that's just a probability.
It's the probability that two strings
will separate. Probabilities are
dimensionless.
Have no dimensions at all.
So, it must be that little g
squared
must be connected to big G
by something that carries dimensions.
What's the What's the units of big G
again?
Length squared. What's the probability
of little g?
Right.
What goes here is the string length
squared. Now, it's dimensionless and
dimensionally consistent.
Now, it's dimensionally consistent.
Area on one side, area on the other. But
it's also true that the Planck length
squared
is L Planck squared.
So, we've just derived
the relationship
between the Planck length, the string
length, and the coupling constant.
Removing the square root,
it's the coupling constant
times the string length is equal to the
Planck length.
Now, typically,
we imagine that g is a small number,
that the probability for strings
breaking up is a small number. If it's a
big number, we don't even know how to
get started in doing string theory. We
typically think of it as a small number.
And so, the Planck length is typically a
small fraction of the string length. But
that's uh we just keep that in mind.
This is
one of our basic equations.
L Planck squared is the Newton constant.
And
L Planck
is equal to the string coupling constant
times the string length scale.
These are two important equations.
Write them down.
If we If we don't get through this
derivation, we may get through it
tonight. We may.
All right, that's one set of facts. One
fact. No, actually there's two facts
there. Excuse me.
Did you say that g
I'm trying to figure if g is greater or
less than one or
Little g is usually less than one. Okay.
Yeah. So, that means that the string
scale is typically bigger than the
Planck scale.
In general, the Planck scale is the
smallest scale that you wind up thinking
about.
String scale can be bigger.
Okay.
Next,
entropy.
Let's start with entropy of black holes.
What's the symbol for entropy?
S.
So, I won't write entropy. I'll write S.
What's BH stand for?
Black holes. You sure it isn't
Bekenstein-Hawking?
Okay.
S black hole is equal to Now, we're not
going to worry very much about the
numerical constants.
First of all,
it's equal to the area of the horizon
divided by g. Does that make sense? Is
this dimensionally consistent? Sure.
Area has units of area and g has units
of area. There's a four in there, but
we're not going to worry about the four.
That's uh
All right, another way we could write it
is to remember that the area is
proportional to the square of the
Schwarzschild radius
divided by g.
And the Schwarzschild radius
is 2mg.
So, this becomes proportional to m
squared g squared.
mg is the radius. m squared g squared is
the area.
And now we can factor out a g.
So, the entropy of a black hole is the
mass squared
times Newton's constant.
But
it's also
the mass squared
times the Planck length squared. All of
these are the same thing.
Mass squared times Planck length
squared, that comes from here.
All right. So, that's the black hole
entropy.
Now, let's think about a string.
Imagine that we have a string.
A little string. A little one. A
graviton.
But now we hit it hard.
We hit it hard and we give it a lot of
energy.
We heat it up.
How do we heat it up? By bombarding it
with a lot of particles or just putting
it in a frying pan or boiling it,
whatever we do with it.
We pump a lot of energy into it. What
happens when we pump a lot of energy
into it? It starts to vibrate. It starts
to oscillate. And typically,
unless we do it in an especially careful
way,
it'll form a big tangle of string.
There it is.
All over the place.
If we heat it up, that's about what
we'll get.
It's like a big warped ball of a big
ball
You know, if you go fishing, you
remember what your reel looks like after
uh you know, the big tangled mess.
Um
Big tangled messes have entropy.
They have entropy just because there are
many, many tangles which
are hard to tell apart.
What's the entropy? The entropy of a
a thing
is the number of configurations which
are hard to tell apart, which are too
hard to tell apart because the pieces
are too small and numerous.
Right? So, a string
a vibrating string like this also has
entropy.
Let's try to guess. Let's try to guess
what the entropy of a vibrating string
is. To do that, I'm going to make a
model.
A very, very simple model of a string.
Uh it's an oversimplification.
It gives the right answer.
It's
It's certainly an oversimplification,
but qualitatively it's the right
picture. And here's the idea. Instead of
thinking of string theory in
ordinary space, let's imagine that space
is replaced by a lattice.
A cubic lattice
that looks like that.
And now, what is a string?
A string is a
collection of
links. The lines of the lattice, just
the terminology.
The lines of the lattice are called
links.
The nodes are called sites, s i t e,
sites, links.
The squares
Do you know what the fancy name for the
squares of a lattice are?
The plaquettes.
The plaquettes, but we're not going to
We're not going to have anything to do
with plaquettes.
All right. So, there's the links of the
lattice, and a string would be a
connected set of links.
In other words, a line or curve through
space is replaced by a sequence of
links.
The links can go back over themselves.
No rule that says the link can't go back
over itself.
But we follow it. And let's say we
follow it from beginning to end.
Imagine now a big jumbled string.
Kind of random walking string.
How many configurations of it are there?
All right. Let's start at one end. We're
going to ignore the question of whether
it's a closed or open string. It doesn't
matter for these purposes. You get the
same answer pretty much.
Supposing you start at one end, how many
possibilities are there?
I've drawn a two-dimensional world.
If it were a three-dimensional world, we
would have some lattice coming out of
the blackboard. If it were a
four-dimensional world, but the basic
picture would be the same. Okay, let's
work with a two-dimensional world for
simplicity.
How many
ways are there of starting out?
Four.
Okay, we get to this one over here.
Could have gone to any four.
What's the next uh
number of ways to continue?
Four. We're allowed to We're allowed to
cut back on ourselves.
times four
Supposing altogether
the string
has little n links.
Incidentally, in this model, I want you
to imagine the size of a link
is the string length, L string.
The size We're doing string theory. So,
why So, what else could it possibly be
if we're doing string theory? Each one
of these is size L string.
Supposing the total length
of the string was n units.
How many uh how many states are there?
4 to the n, right?
Which happens to be 2 to the 2 n.
Let's just write 4 to the n.
Supposing it was a three-dimensional
lattice, what would it be?
6 to the n. It doesn't Whatever it is,
it's some ordinary number to the nth
power.
Supposing it was a lattice which wasn't
a cubic lattice, but was a hexagonal
close-packed lattice or some other
ridiculous lattice. The number would
still be some number to the nth power.
Right?
Now,
what is the definition of the entropy?
That's how many
random states. And in fact, it's an
interesting fact.
Of course, some of them are very
special. There's the one state which is
just a straight line.
That's a pretty rare possibility.
The chances that you would get a
straight line are pretty remote, one out
of 4 to the n if n is large.
If you run this on a computer
and just randomly get a random number
generator and just start generating
string configurations,
and n is relatively large, let's say
100, they'll all look about the same.
They'll all look about They'll form a
ball of random walking stuff. They'll
all look about the same.
Uh the chances that you will get a
untypical
looking string are very, very small.
With 100 links, boy, every day they
really look very similar.
So, that means that the number of states
which are all similar to each other,
hard to tell apart, is 4 to the n.
What's the entropy of that?
n log 4, right?
The entropy is by definition the
logarithm of the number of
Let's call them
macroscopically indistinguishable
states.
So, now we know the entropy of a random
string.
All right, let's put it over here.
S string
is equal to the number of links
times logarithm of 4 or some ordinary
number.
Let's not uh Let's not worry about
logarithm of 4.
It's proportional to the number of links
of the string. In other words, it's
proportional to the length of the
string.
But n is dimensionless. It's just an
integer.
Length
is dimensional.
Has units of whatever units are.
So, how do I make this uh
Well, let's see what am I writing.
Oh, no. I know. This is This is correct.
This is absolute This is correct.
This is correct. But there's another way
that we can write this.
Supposing
the length of the string, and by the
length of the string I mean following it
around,
is L.
L is the length of the string.
How many little
links does it have?
Well, well, well, n, I know. But what is
n? The question is what is n?
L over L string, right?
That's n.
The total length of the string divided
up into these little unit
string lengths, that's n. So, we can
also write
that the entropy of a string
is its length
divided by uh times No, divided by L
string.
Let me rewrite this formula over here.
It's A over G, but G is L Planck
squared.
There's something both similar and
totally different about these formulas.
Area is replaced by length.
L Planck squared is replaced by L
string. They are different. They're not
the same.
They contain different powers.
This is linear in the length. This is
quadratic in the size of the of the of
the thing. Contains L string downstairs.
This one contains L Planck downstairs.
But
you know, there is some
some similarity, but they are different.
Now,
let's rewrite it another way.
In string theory, each one of these
little links has a mass.
The mass of one link, let's let's
consider it.
Let's call it little m
for mass, the mass of one link, l i n k.
What is that equal to?
Okay, in our units, in units Where were
our units?
Our units are up here.
c = h bar = 1.
What's the What's the relationship
between units of mass and units of
length?
Inverse.
A mass is an inverse length.
So, the mass of one of these links in
string theory, since we're doing string
theory, there's only one thing it could
be.
1 over
L string.
So, that's the mass of a link.
Okay.
What about the mass of the whole string?
Let's take the mass of the whole string
now.
I think we can erase this.
What's the mass of the whole long
string? Or the whole ball of uh
N over L string.
But, what is N? I think I lost N.
N
was L over L string.
N itself was L over L string.
And so, the mass of the string
is the length of the string
divided by the square of
It's the length of the string divided by
the string length squared.
Did that make sense?
This is a constant of nature.
Uh with the units of length. This is the
length
following the string.
All right. Following the string around
on its curve.
All right. So, that's M string.
And now, let's eliminate L.
L
is equal to M string
times L string squared.
And let's plug it in
to the formula for entropy. What do I
get?
L
is the mass of the string.
times L string, right?
Did I get it right?
I got it right.
Well, the mass of the Let's not even
call it the mass of the string. The mass
of the of the whole thing, whatever it
is.
In string theory, strings can be
anything. You're a string, I'm a string.
All right? A star is a string.
Or a collection of strings.
So, again, we see something else that's
sort of similar.
The entropy of the string or the entropy
entropy of the black hole is the square
of the mass times the Planck length
squared. The entropy of a string is the
mass of the string times the string
length.
There's a pattern here. There's a
pattern here. It's the wrong pattern.
It's not the pattern we want. Because
after all, what we'd really like to say
is this big ball of tangled string is a
black hole.
Why not? I mean, you know, you take two
strings, you collide them together with
a terrific terrific force. You make a
big jumble of string. What could it
possibly be?
It must be a black hole. But, it's not
working. It's not working. Something's
wrong. Not working, but it's almost
working. Well, not almost working, but
it's working
some pattern is right.
Let's take a little break. I need a
break. You're going to leave us in
suspense?
No, no.
I don't know if we'll get there tonight.
I'm not sure, but uh
but um
You ask too many questions. I didn't
intend to leave you in suspense, but uh
All right. Here are the basic formulas
that you need to follow what I may not
finish tonight.
Uh but, they're simple formulas. So,
write them down.
Look at them and uh
if we don't finish tonight
remember them.
Newton constant, that's nothing but the
Planck area.
Newton constant is the Planck area.
The relation between the Planck length
and the string length is through the
string coupling constant. You know, it
goes this way, not uh the other way.
Black hole entropy
is area divided by Planck area.
And it's also
mass squared
times Planck length squared. We can
forget the G here if we like.
Entropy of a string
is the length of the string instead of
the area
divided by one power of L string.
And it also happens to be one power of
mass.
Not times the Planck length, but by the
string length. That by the string
length.
Those are the basic working
equations that
we'll use.
Now,
in string theory
G is something that you can change.
You can imagine
uh
that the coupling constant G
is something that somebody could have a
knob that could change. Let's not ask
how you build such a knob. It's built
into string theory that uh the things
like coupling constants are things that
could vary.
So, let's imagine that they could vary.
And I'll imagine, but uh let's assume
that they can.
What happens? And let's start.
Let's start our game
with the coupling constant G being very
small.
If it's very small, negligible, maybe
even zero.
If it's zero
strings don't split at all when they
cross each other.
Strings don't split and jump across the
other strings.
There is no gravity.
Gravity is infinitely weak
if
if the string coupling constant is zero.
So, that's a starting point. And now,
let's start
with a
big tangled string.
So much energy has been put into it
that it's massively big.
As big as a star or bigger.
It can't be a black hole. Why can't it
be a black hole? Because the
relationships between the entropy of a
string and the entropy of a black hole
are not right. What it is is a string.
Entropy proportional to its length.
Um now, let's imagine increasing
G, little G. What starts to happen?
What starts to happen
is Let's see, where are we?
Well, what does start to happen as we as
we increase little G?
Splitting. Strings get shorter. Start to
interact. Well, uh
let's hold L string fixed.
It's convenient
It's convenient to work in units in
which L string is held fixed.
So, if G gets
bigger
L Planck gets bigger. But, that's
another way of saying that the
gravitational coupling constant gets
bigger.
That's not too surprising.
If we increase G, it means little
strings can break off.
If they can break off, they can jump
across and gravitation becomes
important.
So, as little G starts to increase
gravity starts to become important.
What happens to this thing as gravity
starts to become important?
Gravity starts to pull it together.
It pulls it together, shrinks the size
of it.
What happens to the energy of it,
incidentally?
Does it increase or decrease?
It decreases.
It decreases. That's because the
gravitational attraction
the potential energy is negative.
And when it gets pulled together, it
lowers the energy.
When an object gets pulled together by
gravity
typically its energy decreases.
So, its mass decreases. But, it becomes
denser.
And at some point, just like any other
object if you squeeze it more and more,
at some point
its structure will pass its
Schwarzschild radius. It'll become
smaller than a Schwarzschild radius, and
what happens?
It becomes a black hole.
So, let's imagine doing this very
slowly. We slowly slowly slowly change
G. The string begins to shrink and
shrink and shrink. And at some Well,
shrink, I mean to say that it uh that it
um
uh the whole ball of thing begins to
contract.
And at some point
it turns into a black hole. I'll tell
you I'll I'll try to tell you when it
turns into a black hole. I'll try to
give you an idea of what the crossover
is between string and black hole.
So,
this end is G equals zero.
No gravity. Gravity has not turned on
yet.
Now, we start increasing G.
The The starts to shrink.
And eventually
when G is large enough
becomes a black hole.
I don't know. This is some value of G.
The value of G depends on the mass of
the object. The more massive it is
the smaller G has to be in order to make
it a black hole.
That's pretty clear. The more massive it
is the more easily it'll become a black
hole.
So, at some point depending on what we
started with, it will become a black
hole.
Now,
the question is is
is G between zero and the value between
zero and one or is it a
big number?
Uh let's say it's between zero and one.
I think it's convenient to say I I think
it's useful to think of it as being
between zero and one. Yeah. Mhm.
Yeah, but not
the story is not pretty when G gets
bigger than one. We don't want to go
there.
Okay.
So, yeah.
Uh and in fact, we're going to continue
to think of G as small.
If G is small, it may take a very big
object
in order to turn into a black hole.
And it will.
All right? So, it may take a rather
large thing to turn into a black hole.
But whatever G is, whatever G is
basically there's an object which is big
enough that when you by the time you
turn G up to that value, it will turn
into a black hole.
Okay, so that's what happens if you
slowly
There's another word for slowly.
adiabatic
Adiabatic is a physicist's fancy term
for changing a control parameter very
slowly, turning a dial very slowly.
So, under an adiabatic change of G
this turns into a black hole.
What would you guess happens if you then
take the black hole and turn G back
again?
You turn it to be so small that there's
not enough gravity to hold the black
hole together. What does it become?
a black hole a black hole a ball of
string A ball of string. What else could
it be? What else could it be? Everything
is a ball of string when you turn off
gravity.
And so
it also goes this way.
Now, there's actually a technical point
here.
It's a technical point about the
relative entropy of a single string and
many strings with the same total amount
of mass.
You might think, well, when you go back
again, perhaps it doesn't turn into a
single string, perhaps it turns into
three disconnected pieces of string or
100,000 disconnected pieces of string.
No, there is a technical point about
counting the number of states of
strings.
And uh
the answer is there are many many more
states of a single string than there are
of multiple strings. That's a little bit
counterintuitive.
You might have thought if I have uh two
string of the same mass.
You take a certain amount of mass and
you divide it up into 10 strings
how many configurations are there
relative to if you took the whole mass
and made one big string out of it? There
are many more configurations of one
string. That's surprising.
And and it's a fact. So, the most likely
thing that you'll get when you go back
is another single string. And so you can
imagine somebody with this dial turning
it one way
string becomes black hole.
Turning it back again, black hole
becomes string and so forth.
Now, what happens
to the stringy stuff
when you turn it to a black hole? Does
the string disappear? Does it get Does
it get sucked into the black hole?
We're watching this thing from the
outside.
It's inside the horizon. It's inside the
horizon. It's not in it, but if we're
watching it from the outside, nothing
ever crosses the horizon.
So, the answer is it's not inside the
black hole. It's on the horizon or near
the horizon of the black hole.
Here it is.
Of course, it's only a a It's only a
good macroscopic size black hole when
the black hole is much bigger than the
string length scale.
And so when the black hole is really
much bigger than the string length
scale, the string the string
is just a little bit of fuzziness on the
horizon.
And that's what you would see from the
outside as you turned up gravitation,
the object would collapse, but you would
see the string sort of collect on the
horizon of the black hole.
Okay.
Let's think about black holes of
different size
relative to the string length scale. The
string length scale is basically the
size of these
loops of string here.
Let's imagine a smaller black hole.
Here's a smaller black hole.
And here's the loops of string.
Do you think it makes sense to think
about a black hole which is itself much
smaller than the
lengths of the loops of
string which make up which make up the
black hole?
Well, there's no way you can answer that
other than to know a little bit more
about string theory than we've talked
about. But the answer is no. The point
at which the Schwarzschild radius gets
as small as the loops of string
that's the transition point.
All right? So, if you imagined
if you imagined um
varying the constants
so that the relative size of the
Schwarzschild radius and the string
length scale varied, somehow you did
that.
Then at the point where the string
length scale is comparable to the
Schwarzschild radius
that's the point at which
uh
the black hole becomes a string or the
string becomes a black hole. It's
another way to say it. It's also the
point at which the black hole does not
have enough mass to create a
gravitational field to hold the string
down onto it.
The fluctuations of the string will
simply uh cause it to
float up off the horizon.
So
um
one more element
in this going back and forth between
strings and black holes
the point the point
of separation between strings and black
holes
Let's call it the transition point.
The transition point
transition
is when the Schwarzschild radius
Oops.
is when the Schwarzschild radius R
Schwarzschild
is equal or approximately equal to the
string length scale.
If the Schwarzschild black hole radius
is smaller than these little loops of
string, it doesn't mean anything anymore
to say it's a black hole. It just
becomes a string.
This is the string This is the
transition point. Let's rewrite it.
Uh the Schwarzschild radius is what? M
times G.
M
Two's don't count. We don't We don't
care about two's.
Two are equal to one.
And G is equal to L Planck squared.
Actually, we can go one step further,
can't we?
We can relate L Planck to L string.
Let's see, which way shall we do this?
Let's get rid of L Planck in this
formula here.
Uh
So, this would be Yeah.
Let's rewrite this.
M
times L Planck squared, that's G squared
L string squared
is L string. Let's go back over what I
did. I'm just going to do it again for
you.
Do the steps again.
Schwarzschild radius
equals L string. Schwarzschild radius is
M G.
equals L string.
G
That's mass times L Planck squared
equals L string.
And now we use
that L Planck is G times L string.
So, this is M Planck G squared
L string squared equals L string. Did I
do that right?
Yeah.
I think we can cancel something here,
can't we?
equals one.
Ah, I didn't You're right, I didn't
write a one. I will now do it.
Okay, so let's see what that means.
Um
For a given mass
as you start to decrease the coupling
constant G
this quantity here will eventually go
down to about one and then that's the
point at which the transition between
strings and black holes takes place.
All right, so we need to know this
equation here.
Up there you wrote that the entropies
are equal.
Of what?
Uh
You wrote
M L P squared, I thought.
Which is equal to L S.
Well, so far I haven't even talked about
entropy. I mean, I talked about entropy
earlier. No, but
I think that you have M squared L P
squared and if you
factor out M from that, you get the
lower equation. So
Which one? This one?
It looks like the entropies will be
equated. It's true. We're going to
Yeah.
I just want to lay down all the
equations for you.
We're not going to finish it tonight and
then I want you to go and study those
equations.
Remind yourselves about that and then
we're going to put them together. We're
going to put them together and out of
them we're going to see a derivation of
the entropy of a black hole.
Uh
coming from the entropy of strings.
We're basically going to derive this
formula
from this formula.
String theory derives black hole
entropy.
Okay, there's one more element, one more
moving part. I'm trying to lay out all
the parts. It's a
It's a It's In a sense, it's a simple
argument. We don't even need an
integral.
Not even a derivative, let alone an
integral. But on the other hand, there's
some logical pieces there which are kind
of intricate. So, I'll try to go slowly
and spell them out.
One more.
It's the fact that when you change a
system adiabatically
you have a control parameter
coupling constant, a magnetic field, an
electric field and you and you have some
system in it. It could be um
a box of uh
a container of fluid gas and the whole
thing is in a huge magnetic field
and you slowly slowly slowly vary the
magnetic field.
What happens to the entropy?
It's a constant. It doesn't change.
You turn the magnetic field up, all
sorts of things happen. The energy
changes, the volume might change because
the gas might press against the All
kinds of stuff happens. The one thing
that doesn't happen is the entropy
doesn't change.
This is partly a consequence of
something which I've emphasized over and
over in these lectures, the conservation
of information.
Entropy is hidden information.
When you change When you change the
environment, not the environment in
terms of the atmosphere and things like
that, but when you take a control
parameter and you slowly change it
the amount of
hidden information doesn't change.
That's the same as saying entropy
doesn't change.
So, in a
adiabatic process like we're talking
about here where you slowly change the
coupling constant the entropy doesn't
change. So, that's one more thing.
Let's just write it down.
Uh
I'll just write it. Adiabatic
change
of
anything, but in particular G
does not change the entropy.
Question. Wouldn't that be contingent on
going through a phase transition like
steam to water or water to gas? Yeah, it
is contingent on not going through a
phase transition.
Uh but phase transitions are
characteristic of infinite systems.
Phase transitions, strictly strict phase
transitions only happen when a system
has infinite volume. Systems of finite
volume never have, strictly speaking, a
phase transitions.
Um
If you go slow enough, if you go slow
enough with your change, the uh the
entropy doesn't change for a finite
system.
The statement that said that a long
string
has more entropy than having a set of
smaller strings. That That sounds so
sort of uh
In a certain volume, in a volume. You
fix a volume, you put enough string in
there to more or less fill the volume
and now you think about the possibility
of one long string versus uh versus
several Yeah.
It would seem so, doesn't it? Yeah.
Right? Happens not to be true by
explicit calculation.
Um
There is a reason.
Uh Yeah, I'll tell I'll tell you what.
Let's do it next time. Remind me next
time. There There is a reason and it's
it's actually simple. It's a surprising
but simple thing.
Um
Okay, so what's what's what's the
strategy going to be? The strategy is
going to be to start with a a black
hole.
Start with a black hole
with a given mass. We're going to start
with a black hole with a given mass
at a given coupling constant. Let's call
it M naught and G naught.
This is our target object. This is what
we're interested in. A black hole of
mass M naught when the coupling constant
is G naught.
And now we're going to start slowly
changing G naught. As we slowly change G
naught, the character of this object,
its mass, its whole structure is going
to change.
And it's going to morph and eventually
when G is small enough
namely at this transition point, it's
going to turn into a string.
Okay.
Once it turns it Sorry, does it start as
a string or a black hole?
No, it starts as a black hole. Oh, it
starts as Starts as a black hole and now
we start decreasing G
until it turns into a string.
Once it turns into a string
we use string theory to tell what the
entropy is.
But the entropy couldn't have changed
during that process because
entropy just doesn't change during an
adiabatic process.
So, once it's turned into a string, we
can then use string theory to say what
the entropy is and in that way figure
out what the original black hole entropy
was. As simple as that.
Okay, we're going to do it.
And what we're going to show is when you
do it
this formula for the string
becomes this formula for the black hole.
Okay.
So, that's a remarkable fact that
uh that
uh
And it's been checked for many many many
different kinds of black holes, rotating
black holes, charged black holes, higher
dimensional black holes. It's not an
accident of
uh
of a little bit of uh you know, an
accidental agreement. It's something
which has been checked for a wide wide
variety of different kinds of black
holes.
Uh
rotating, not rotating, charged,
uncharged, magnetically charged, higher
dimensional, you name it.
Uh so
in that sense
there's a good candidate for the
understanding of the entropy of a black
hole and if you like
in some
rough and ready sense
it's just the stringy stuff
that's trapped near the horizon when the
uh when the black hole forms.
Quick question. Yeah. Um
The
The The string with the greatest entropy
is one string.
And what you said The string of a given
length or a given mass. Remember, the
mass is proportional to its length.
Right. So, if you have a given mass of
string
where you've turned off gravity. We've
turned In the process of turning off
gravity, it became a string.
Once it becomes a string
the
a string that would fill a certain
volume of a total mass M
the uh the entropy is greatest for the
string.
But But you also said that there's a
finite probability it may end up being
two strings instead of There's a finite
probability it may end up being two
strings. And in fact, the answer would
not change very much
if it were two strings.
One string, you get an answer. Two
strings, you get a similar answer.
Uh
It doesn't break up into a lot of
strings. If it broke up into a lot of
strings, you'd get a very different
answer.
Right? So,
the statistical counting, I mean, it's a
fancy kind of statistical mechanics of
counting configurations
and saying when you go back and forth,
the black hole, which is in a sense the
maximum entropy that you can squeeze in
a region of space,
morphs into the maximum entropy that you
can contain on a string.
So, it's a very interesting logic.
And we can carry it out for the simplest
case. Beyond the simplest case, it's too
hard, but uh
Okay, let's uh
All right, well, uh
we'll finish this argument next week.
For more, please visit us at
stanford.edu.